<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-08T10:04:20+00:00</updated><id>https://fahimfaisal.info/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fahim Faisal</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">UndocuAlly Training</title><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2022/undocually/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UndocuAlly Training"/><published>2022-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2022/undocually</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2022/undocually/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-details">The details</h1> <ul> <li>Date: 22 July, 2022</li> <li>Speakers: Stephanie Roberts</li> <li>Title: UndocuAlly Training</li> <li>Host: Center for Inclusion and Social Change</li> </ul> <h1 id="the-notes">The notes</h1> <p>I’m not going to put a ton of details here out of respect for all the work that went into the workshop!</p> <p>The main topics included:</p> <ul> <li>Who are our undocumented students?</li> <li>History of exclusionary immigrant policies in the US</li> <li>How citizenship impacts education</li> <li>ASSET program in Colorado and DACA/DREAM act in US</li> <li>Ways to support undocumented students on campus</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="professional-development"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The details Date: 22 July, 2022 Speakers: Stephanie Roberts Title: UndocuAlly Training Host: Center for Inclusion and Social Change]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022 Book Log</title><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2022/book-log/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022 Book Log"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2022/book-log</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2022/book-log/"><![CDATA[<p>A list of books I have read this year!</p> <ol> <li>Children of Dune by Frank Herbert</li> <li>Go Tell the Bees That I Am Gone by Diana Gabaldon</li> <li>Sir Thursday by Garth Nix</li> <li>Drowned Wednesday by Garth Nix</li> <li>Grim Tuesday by Garth Nix</li> <li>Mister Monday by Garth Nix</li> <li>Sabriel by Garth Nix</li> <li>To Hold the Bridge by Garth Nix</li> <li>Wintering by Katherine May</li> <li>Lady Friday by Garth Nix</li> <li>Superior Saturday by Garth Nix</li> <li>Lord Sunday by Garth Nix</li> <li>Lirael by Garth Nix</li> <li>Project Hail Mary by Andy Weir</li> <li>Lisey’s Story by Stephen King</li> <li>The School for Good Mothers by Jessamine Chan</li> <li>God Emperor of Dune by Frank Herbert</li> <li>My Annihilation by Fuminori Nakamura</li> <li>We Cast a Shadow by Maurice Carlos Ruffin</li> <li>Abhorsen by Garth Nix</li> <li>The Every by Dave Eggers</li> <li>A Touch of Ruin by Scarlett St. Clair</li> <li>A Touch of Darkness by Scarlett St. Clair</li> <li>The Echo Wife by Sarah Gailey</li> <li>The Push by Ashley Audrain</li> <li>Cloud Cuckoo Land by Anthony Doerr</li> <li>A Touch of Malice by Scarlett St. Clair</li> <li>Lot by Bryan Washington</li> </ol> <p>In progress (or on hold)</p> <ul> <li>10 Great Mysteries by Edgar Allen Poe</li> <li>There There by Tommy Orange</li> <li>Heretics of Dune by Frank Herbert</li> <li>The Book of Accidents by Chuck Wendig</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="lists"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A list of books I have read this year!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hidden Curriculum Workshop</title><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/hidden-curriculum/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hidden Curriculum Workshop"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/hidden-curriculum</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/hidden-curriculum/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-details">The details</h1> <ul> <li>Date: 10 August, 2021</li> <li>Speakers: Shane Oshetski and Roberto Arruda</li> <li>Title: Uncovering the Hidden Curriculum and Utilizing Transparent Assignments</li> <li>Host: Center for Teaching &amp; Learning at CU Boulder, part of the Equitable Teaching Conference</li> </ul> <h1 id="the-notes">The notes</h1> <p>What is the hidden curriculum?</p> <ul> <li>implicit norms and expectations which are not formally communicated to students</li> <li>these are often placed within a dominant learning culture</li> <li>the hidden curriculum defines a “right” way of thinking, speaking, looking, and behaving based on the dominant culture</li> </ul> <p>Who is affected by the hidden curriculum?</p> <ul> <li>first generation students</li> <li>international students</li> <li>students with different linguistic practices (such as ESL)</li> <li>anyone not familiar with the dominant sociocultural norms</li> </ul> <p>What are some examples of the hidden curriculum? Participants in the workshop submitted objectives that they wanted students to learn in their class, but weren’t included on the formal curriculum.</p> <ul> <li>time management skills</li> <li>working effectively in groups</li> <li>writing coherent essays</li> <li>interpreting technical figures</li> <li>asking for assignment extensions when needed</li> <li>networking with professor and classmates</li> <li>going to office hours</li> </ul> <p>What is transparent instruction?</p> <ul> <li>the goal is to make the expectations for success clear to students</li> <li>in addition to delivering content, explain why the class is structured in such a way</li> <li>create common language around expectations (e.g., in Bloom’s taxonomy, what does Analysis mean?)</li> <li>use a problem-centered approach, but make sure the problem is relevant to everyone</li> </ul> <p>Components of a transparent assignment:</p> <ul> <li>Purpose: is the goal to practice a skill or gain new knowledge? Why is this assignment important? How does it relate to other assignments?</li> <li>Task: what needs to be accomplished? What are the steps?</li> <li>Criteria: what does a successful attempt look like? How will it be graded (provide a rubric)? What is an example of excellence?</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="professional-development"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The details Date: 10 August, 2021 Speakers: Shane Oshetski and Roberto Arruda Title: Uncovering the Hidden Curriculum and Utilizing Transparent Assignments Host: Center for Teaching &amp; Learning at CU Boulder, part of the Equitable Teaching Conference]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with redirect</title><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/redirect/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with redirect"/><published>2021-07-04T17:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-04T17:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/redirect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/redirect/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[you can also redirect to assets like pdf]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Encouraging Presence Workshop</title><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/encouraging-presence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Encouraging Presence Workshop"/><published>2021-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/encouraging-presence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/encouraging-presence/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-details">The details</h1> <ul> <li>Date: 26 January 2021</li> <li>Speaker: CTL fellows</li> <li>Title: Encouraging Presence</li> <li>Host: CU Boulder Center for Teaching and Learning</li> </ul> <h1 id="the-notes">The notes</h1> <ul> <li>Quick check-in to see how people are doing: annotate on zoom slide</li> <li>Vulnerability: being willing to admit your mistakes and sharing your own personal experiences</li> <li>Flexibility: when class format is uncertain, check in with students to see what their needs are. You may need to adapt based on the energy students are bringing into the class.</li> <li>Give a variety of opportunities for students to be engaged. Be persistent in advertising your office hours and make them fun. Start each class with a quick breakout room with some reflection questions about life and the course content.</li> <li>Don’t just teach to the top third of the class, who are already engaged and attentive</li> <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1SFYLMBVibHXTisdyw316krEcZdhnZM9Mh2i3G8IAA6o/edit">Some ideas compiled by the speakers</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="professional-development"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The details Date: 26 January 2021 Speaker: CTL fellows Title: Encouraging Presence Host: CU Boulder Center for Teaching and Learning]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Student Mental Health Workshop</title><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/student-mental-health/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Student Mental Health Workshop"/><published>2021-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/student-mental-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/student-mental-health/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-details">The details</h1> <ul> <li>Date: 25 January 2021</li> <li>Speaker: <a href="https://www.colorado.edu/clinicalpsychology/june-gruber-phd">Dr. June Gruber</a></li> <li>Title: Promoting Student Well-Being During the COVID-19 Pandemic</li> <li>Host: CU Boulder Center for Teaching and Learning</li> </ul> <h1 id="the-notes">The notes</h1> <ul> <li>College is a time of resilience. Students are developing identity and agency as well as maturing in cognition and self control.</li> <li>However, students are very vulnerable to depression, reckless behavior, and above-average suicidal thoughts</li> <li>Since COVID-19, depression has increased and mental health challenges have impaired academics.</li> <li>However, substance abuse seems to be decreasing, so effects of the pandemic are varied.</li> <li>What we can do to address college mental health <ul> <li>De-stigmatize student mental illness: acknowledge that stress and mental illness are normal. We can change our language to not make fun of those with mental health difficulties. Make it easy for students to ask for resources and support.</li> <li>Empower students with science: our ideas of what will make us happy and what actually makes us happy often do not match. We can provide students with resources that can be used by anyone. This can be in the form of a syllabus statement and posting local resources on Canvas.</li> <li>Take a citizen science approach: if we want to support our students, we need to engage with discussion on their experience. There are many research opportunities available on campus that also provide financial compensation.</li> <li>Cultivate empathy: this situation is not normal for anyone, so we need to grant ourselves and our students kindness as we move through this situation.</li> </ul> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="professional-development"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The details Date: 25 January 2021 Speaker: Dr. June Gruber Title: Promoting Student Well-Being During the COVID-19 Pandemic Host: CU Boulder Center for Teaching and Learning]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Accessibility and Accommodations Workshop</title><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/accessibility-accommodations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accessibility and Accommodations Workshop"/><published>2021-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/accessibility-accommodations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/accessibility-accommodations/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-details">The details</h1> <ul> <li>Date: 21 January 2021</li> <li>Speaker: Laura Hamrick and Ellie Brigger</li> <li>Title: Disability Access: What You Need to Know as an Instructor</li> <li>Host: CU Boulder Center for Teaching and Learning</li> </ul> <h1 id="the-notes">The notes</h1> <ul> <li>link to the slides <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1LGVpoceYPrhPVi3uXnBXcbL_Sm7-QMNuW8WqRhk-GGY/edit#slide=id.p">here</a></li> <li>Who’s who in accessibility at CU Boulder <ul> <li>Disability services: accommodations for students</li> <li>ADA office: accommodations for employees</li> <li>Digital Accessibility Office, Universal Design for Learning Service: proactive accessibility</li> <li>OIT and CTL: additional support and resources</li> </ul> </li> <li>Student Accommodations through Disability Services <ul> <li>Disabilities that are not visible are much more common than visible disabilities</li> <li>Biggest categories are psychological, learning disabilities, and ADHD</li> <li>About 1/10 students at CU use the office for accommodations</li> <li>Office manages accommodation letters between students and faculty online</li> <li>Extended time on assignments and quizzes on canvas <a href="https://oit.colorado.edu/services/teaching-learning-applications/canvas/accessibility/providing-extended-time-accommodations">link</a></li> <li>Flexibility with attendance and assignment deadlines <a href="https://www.colorado.edu/disabilityservices/accommodations/flexibility-attendance-and-assignment-deadlines-plan-flex-plan">link</a></li> </ul> </li> <li>Proactive Accessibility <ul> <li>Public facing videos (not on Canvas) should be proactively captioned</li> <li>Accommodation is reactive (response to a request), while Accessibility is proactive (removing barriers)</li> <li>Accessibility is important because people should be able to access your content immediately. It is stressful and draining to continually ask for accommodations</li> <li>Top tips <ul> <li>use files with real text, not images of text. Don’t use scans of paper documents. Use HTML and Word docs. PDFs should be OCR’d for screen readers (see SensusAccess). for more complex images like maps, provide general alt-text with general trends and take-aways</li> <li>caption videos. Helps for students that are hard of hearing, English is not first language, attention disabilities, and when you use a lot of technical language</li> <li>share your slides, outlines, and recordings. make a note of this so students don’t need to stress about taking notes during the class and can look back on the material later. Students might miss part of your lecture due to internet or other issues.</li> <li>Allow time for accessibility conversations. This means listing textbooks in the bookstore, giving early access to Canvas, and sharing materials with Disability services</li> <li>check in with your students</li> </ul> </li> </ul> </li> <li>Main takeaway: providing accessible resources helps more than just students with disabilities. I will try to make course content available in as many ways as possible so it is easy to access.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="professional-development"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The details Date: 21 January 2021 Speaker: Laura Hamrick and Ellie Brigger Title: Disability Access: What You Need to Know as an Instructor Host: CU Boulder Center for Teaching and Learning]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Personal Values Quiz</title><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/personal-values/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Personal Values Quiz"/><published>2021-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/personal-values</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/personal-values/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the topics we discussed in the recent Endurance PhD Intensive was the importance of matching your goals with your personal values. I just completed <a href="https://personalvalu.es/personal-values-list">this quiz</a> to rank my top values. I originally selected 22 values from the list, and the quiz reported my top 5 <a href="https://personalvalu.es/results/4309691d-3384-45fe-aace-55fdb394aae6">results here</a>. This quiz was difficult because I felt like so many of the values were related to me. The way I made my decision in a tie was ask which value was <em>a result of</em> the other value? More details of how I nested these values is below.</p> <ol> <li><em>Authenticity</em>. I interpret this as being genuine and truthful about my goals, ambitions, and values. I feel uncomfortable when I lie to other people. Some values that stem from Authenticity are: uniqueness, honesty, curiosity</li> <li><em>Accountability</em>. I interpret this as being someone that other people can count on. If I say I’m going to do something, I will deliver. I never want to be considered the flaky friend. Some values that stem from Accountability are: loyalty, honesty, commitment</li> <li><em>Certainty</em>. I don’t like surprises. I prefer having a schedule that stays the same from day to day. This leaves me mental energy to work on more important things. However, I am working on being more flexible when necessary! Some values that stem from Certainty are: security, financial stability, trust</li> <li><em>Control</em>. I want to have as much information about my situation as possible, especially when making a decision. This is what allows me to maintain certainty and accountability. Some values that stem from Control are: peace, appreciation, privacy</li> <li><em>Discipline</em>. I like to be oriented towards a long-term goal. I haven’t been good at resisting temptation (like sugar or sleeping in) lately, but I am working towards building up that stamina again. Some values that stem from Discipline are: growth (another big one for me), excellence, respect, challenge</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="professional-development"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the topics we discussed in the recent Endurance PhD Intensive was the importance of matching your goals with your personal values. I just completed this quiz to rank my top values. I originally selected 22 values from the list, and the quiz reported my top 5 results here. This quiz was difficult because I felt like so many of the values were related to me. The way I made my decision in a tie was ask which value was a result of the other value? More details of how I nested these values is below.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Endurance PhD Intensive</title><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/endurance-phd-intensive/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Endurance PhD Intensive"/><published>2021-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/endurance-phd-intensive</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/endurance-phd-intensive/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-details">The details</h1> <ul> <li>Date: January 11 through January 13</li> <li>Speaker: Leslie Blood</li> <li>Title: Endurance PhD Intensive</li> <li>Host: CU Boulder Graduate School Professional Development</li> </ul> <h1 id="the-notes">The notes</h1> <p>This workshop is a condensed version of the weekly productivity seminars I have been attending over the last semester. Each day of the workshop has a different theme, but all of the ideas will tie together. If you are a grad student at CU Boulder, consider signing up for the seminars <a href="https://www.colorado.edu/graduateschool/endurance-phd">here</a>! I have found them to be very motivating.</p> <h2 id="day-1-the-four-tendencies">Day 1: The Four Tendencies</h2> <ul> <li>The theory of four Tendencies is from Gretchen Rubin (take the quiz <a href="https://quiz.gretchenrubin.com">here</a>).</li> <li>Your tendency describes how you respond to external and internal expectations. <ul> <li>For example, I am a questioner, which means I have no problem working to meet inner expectations, but I resist outer expectations unless I understand why it is important. That means I need to understand <em>why</em> I am doing something; saying “because I said so” is not motivating in the slightest.</li> <li>One of the difficulties questioners face is that they can talk themselves into and out of anything. If I don’t feel like doing reading for research one day, I can make up a bunch of excuses like “the internet is bad today” or “it’s more urgent that the laundry gets folded”. Leslie calls this action “spotting loopholes”. This is dangerous because you can talk yourself out of doing anything if you are not in the mood. Additionally, this burns a lot of mental energy while you are figuring out what to do that day. You can’t depend on willpower to last forever!</li> <li>Some of the most helpful strategies for questioners: develop clarity of purpose, be mindful of spotting loopholes, monitor trends in productivity, and be able to distinguish why one behavior is better than another so you feel justified in continuing the behavior.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Why are looking at tendencies helpful? <ul> <li>Understanding your motivation helps develop resilience and lowers barriers to getting things done. You can set up systems that let you make less decisions about what to do.</li> <li>Predictability increases happiness because it decreases stress</li> </ul> </li> <li>If you have an addictive personality, you need to abstain from the things that are bad for you. For example, if you can’t just have 2 Oreos, then probably stay away from Oreos altogether. While I have been fortunate to not suffer from substance addiction, I do think I have an addictive personality. I can’t do something halfway, whether that is reading books about running, trying out a new productivity system, or meal planning. This tends to lead to burnout and frustration. I can make rules to moderate, but find they feel too restrictive, or I can always rationalize why I don’t need to follow the rule this time. To avoid this, I should identify behaviors that are harmful (at the moment I’m mostly thinking of sugar) and make a plan to avoid them.</li> <li>We will engage in behaviors that are more convenient and avoid behaviors that are inconvenient. Will come back to this more when we talk about forming habits!</li> <li>You don’t have separate personal and professional personalities. If you are a questioner, then that tendency applies to both work and home.</li> <li>One possible way to motivate change is a “lightening bolt”. As a questioner, you need to keep in mind the reason this motivated you in order to keep up momentum. For me, this usually happens when I read an especially good book or when I get so sick of my bad habits that I want to jump start a new system of habits.</li> <li>What happens when inner expectations are in conflict with outer expectations? Go back to make sure your values are being reflected in your decisions. Will come back to this more when we talk about values.</li> <li>Habits are important so you don’t spend all your energy making decisions. You need to trust your plan more than your feelings in the moment.</li> <li>Short term vs. long term goals are a constant struggle of urgent vs. important tasks (see <a href="https://www.eisenhower.me/eisenhower-matrix/">Eisenhower Matrix</a>) <ul> <li>To prioritize important things, need to create space to do it every day to remove resistance (even if it is only 15 minutes at first). The important work will get prioritized in productivity blocks, while urgent things can happen during other times of the day.</li> <li>You also need to accept that things aren’t going to be perfect the first time. You can’t improve on it until it is outside of your brain!</li> </ul> </li> <li>What if you really hate doing the thing? You need to think about how the task is getting you to your big-picture goal. Also the thing is piling up while you are procrastinating!</li> <li>How do advocate for your productivity needs when you are not in a position of power? <ul> <li>I have definitely struggled with this as a graduate student. Some areas where this may come up is expectations about responding to emails and scheduling meetings at all times throughout the week, even though you have peak productivity hours at certain times of day.</li> <li>Hopefully your advisor or supervisor is open to hearing your thoughts on this, since it benefits them for you to be more productive!</li> <li>If they won’t budge, then keep in mind that this position is only temporary.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h2 id="day-2-habits-and-automation">Day 2: Habits and Automation</h2> <ul> <li>What are we going to automate? <ul> <li>This determines what we need to spend mental energy on.</li> <li>For example, you can eliminate choices like what to eat, what to wear, when to get up</li> <li>Questioners can really benefit from automated habits because it reduces decision making fatigue</li> </ul> </li> <li>Anchor habits are non-negotiable things that happen every day <ul> <li>For example, this could be having a cup of coffee or brushing your teeth</li> <li>Transitions are important for differentiating between parts of the day. When working from home, you are missing the classical commute, so you will need to be more creative about making a difference between work time and personal time. For example, get a curtain to separate work desk and sleeping area of your room.</li> </ul> </li> <li>What is a good habit? A sticky habit <ul> <li>Sticky habits have strong triggers. Most people react well to visual triggers, like setting out your medication by the coffee maker for the next morning.</li> <li>Sticky habits also have easy wins without many barriers. This means you can get a quick victory to feel good, and it is not difficult to accomplish.</li> <li>Regularly winning at easy habits allows you to rebuild confidence in your ability to accomplish things</li> <li>Need to pace yourself when making new habits. You need to work up to manageable behaviors. Building momentum is more important than the initial small results.</li> </ul> </li> <li>When taking out a bad habit, it often helps to add in a better substitute. For example, substituting popcorn as a crunchy snack instead of potato chips.</li> <li>How to deal with resistance to habits <ul> <li>Be careful about “moral licensing” which can give you an out if you aren’t feeling like doing it</li> <li>Think about the reasons behind your resistance and remember your reasons for starting the habit</li> <li>Work on new habits when you have energy during the day. Don’t try to do new things when your energy budget is drained!</li> <li>Try habit pairing. Take something you like (tea) and pair it with a new habit that isn’t as fun (writing a paper)</li> </ul> </li> <li>Building systems: cue-behavior-reward <ul> <li>Cue: something that reminds you to do the action. Cues can be location based (kitchen, bathroom), time based (after waking up), visual based (setting out vitamins to refill).</li> <li>Behavior: the action you want to do as a result of the cue</li> <li>Reward: something to make you feel good for doing the behavior so you want to do it again. For some people, this can just be the satisfaction of checking it off of a list. For others, this could be through habit pairing with a treat or fun activity. For me, I’m not good at moderating so the treat option doesn’t really make sense. I also don’t like spending money as a reward, and am trying to not associate food with rewards. Thankfully I do enjoy checking things off!</li> <li>You can also reward yourself with time off. If you reserve your nights and weekends, then it can be motivating to get your work done during the day so you can feel no guilt about not doing work.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h2 id="day-3-values-and-energy-budget">Day 3: Values and Energy Budget</h2> <ul> <li>To start off take <a href="https://personalvalu.es/personal-values-test">this test</a> to see what your top values are. Don’t select things you <em>wish</em> were your values or things you admire in other people. Your values don’t have to be sexy or exciting, but they will help you pick goals that are motivating.</li> <li>You will have to train yourself to do a lot of things you don’t want to do, especially during grad school. You need to remember what your reasons are for being here to get your degree!</li> <li>Starting new habits <ul> <li>You need to have clarity on why you are doing the thing and your goals. You need to write down these goals and schedule the plan, such as a planner or notebook.</li> <li>Frequency: first step in developing a habit. Work on doing the habit every day, even if it is 5 minutes. If your goal is writing, even opening a word document on the weekends and writing 2 sentences helps with frequency. The purpose of this step is to remove resistance to doing the action.</li> <li>Duration: once you have lowered resistance to doing the habit every day, then focus on doing the behavior for longer. Once you are writing every day, work on writing for longer periods of time.</li> <li>Intensity: once you are getting the time in, work on tweaking your habit and environment to get the most done in the amount of time you have. This strongly depends on the energy budget. For example, with COVID and working from home, intensity is the first thing to go since our typical triggers and habits have changed.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Setting goals <ul> <li>Leslie does not recommend setting task-oriented goals. For example, long term goal is “write chapter 2 by end of the semester” and short term goal is “write introduction today”. The problem with these goals is that there are so many things outside of your control, like if the server crashes or your collaborator won’t respond to you.</li> <li>Instead, consider setting goals that are time-oriented. We can control how we spend our 4-hour time blocks, regardless of how much gets done during that time.</li> <li>Finding the right planner can be super helpful. Some recommendations are Productivity Planner, Self Planner for questioners, and Clever Fox planner for obligers.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Lost some steam taking notes on this today, but see my notes about my personal values. I am going to make a point of doing some goal setting and planning with my roommate who also went through the intensive this week!</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="professional-development"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The details Date: January 11 through January 13 Speaker: Leslie Blood Title: Endurance PhD Intensive Host: CU Boulder Graduate School Professional Development]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Writing a Statement of Purpose</title><link href="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/statement-of-purpose/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Writing a Statement of Purpose"/><published>2021-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/statement-of-purpose</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fahimfaisal.info/blog/2021/statement-of-purpose/"><![CDATA[<p>When I was applying to grad school, I had no idea what to include in my statement of purpose. My statement ended up including big, lofty topics and goals that I could never reach during the course of the PhD. After helping others with their applications, here are my personal thoughts on content and how to structure the statement of purpose.</p> <p><em>Disclaimer:</em> These guidelines are biased towards PhD programs or other programs that are research-based. The content will need some tweaking if you are applying for a professional Masters program, for example.</p> <h1 id="purpose">Purpose</h1> <p>The goal of the statement of purpose is to convince a potential advisor that you will be a good fit in their lab group. That means you need to show you have the relevant skills and experience (or are willing to learn the needed skills) to contribute to their research and your general research interests align with theirs. If you aren’t applying for a research program, then you will need to show that you will fit in with the department values and the program will help you achieve your professional goals.</p> <h1 id="structure">Structure</h1> <p>The statement of purpose is typically 1-2 pages. In this short space, you need to tell a cohesive story that will meet the goals discussed above. Below is my suggestion for how to organize your information:</p> <ol> <li>What are your big goals? These are usually career-based. For example, you may want to become research faculty at an R1 university. This is just a brief intro, so only spend 1-2 sentences on this.</li> <li>What do you want to study that will lead you to this goal? This is where you get into the details of your intended research question. If you aren’t doing a research program, this could be the area of industry you want to work in and what specialty classes you want to take. If possible, make this section as specific as possible; this will demonstrate that you have put serious thought into your goals and you already have some knowledge of the field you want to go into. For example, your research question could be “I want to study how teachers use analytics dashboards”. You could also add some details about why you think this is an important question. Some examples that are bad are “I want to study machine learning” or “I would be interested in studying brain signal processing, programming languages, or NLP for low-resource languages”. In the first case, this is way too broad. There are a lot of people doing machine learning, so it won’t convince a potential advisor that you want to do the research that they are doing. In the second case, it sounds like you have no idea what you want to study and are sort of interested in a handful of random topics. Your goal is to show that you are serious. You can always change your mind on a research topic once you get into the program! This section should be a few sentences.</li> <li>What is your story that led you to this goal? This is where you can get into more details about your personal experience. Maybe you had a great teacher who used a particular tool to help their students and you wonder how you can make it better. You could talk about your related work or research experience that led to this question. This section can be a few paragraphs.</li> <li>What skills and experience do you have that will make you good at studying this? This is where you can get technical. If you have previous research experience, brag about it! Talk about the responsibilities you had. Much of this stuff will already be on your resume, but you should elaborate on it to tell a full story. On the other hand, do not try to fit in every single bullet point on your resume.</li> <li>What about this program makes you want to study there? This is perhaps one of the most important parts of the statement. This shows that you know what you are getting into and are serious about your application. For example, I applied to CU because I wanted to do the combined Cognitive Science PhD program; since I’m not a traditional computer science student, I was looking for an interdisciplinary department which would allow me to take classes in a variety of subjects. Especially for research programs, it is important to list a few specific faculty you want to work with. This will help the admissions committee direct your application to the right people to read. For example, you could mention that you want to work with Dr. Adams because their work in human-robot dancing is relevant to your experience.</li> </ol> <h1 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h1> <p>The statement of purpose is your chance to let potential advisors know what kind of student you will be. Are you an independent worker? Do you have extensive experience in this area already? Are you really excited to work on their projects? This is your opportunity to show that you have researched this specific program; people want to know there is a good chance you will come to the school if you are accepted, compared to the other schools you are applying to. You can also use the statement to explain any other parts of your application that are a little lacking (for example, circumstances leading to a bad GPA one semester, lack of research opportunities at your undergrad). This probably doesn’t need to be said, but do not lie in your statement! It’s easy to feel overwhelmed when looking at the accomplishments of others. If you feel like you aren’t interesting enough, talk to someone with an outside perspective who can tell you how awesome you are.</p> <p>If you want another set of eyes on your application or have questions, please reach out!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="advice"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When I was applying to grad school, I had no idea what to include in my statement of purpose. My statement ended up including big, lofty topics and goals that I could never reach during the course of the PhD. After helping others with their applications, here are my personal thoughts on content and how to structure the statement of purpose.]]></summary></entry></feed>